Guide to the Records of the Center for Haitian Studies 1967-1975 (Bulk 1967-1968) RISM RG 11
New York University Archives
Records of the Center for Haitian Studies
Bulk, 1967-1968
1967-1975
RISM RG 11
New York University Archives
6.0 linear feet
The initial proposal for the Center for Haitian Studies took place at the Conference on Resources and Research in Hait i, held in New York City, November 1-4, 1967. During its relatively brief existence, the Center helped focus attention on critical issues in Haiti under the Duvalier government and provided research and training opportunities for Haitians living abroad or in exile. The bilingual collection includes correspondence, financial records, reports, minutes, statutes, press releases, clippings, draft material, published conference proceedings, transcripts, articles, printed matter, audiotapes, notes, and ephemera.
Center for Haitian Studies.
Provenance
The Center for Haitian Studies Collection was created by founding members Dr. Emerson Douyon of the University of Montreal; Dr. Francois Latortue of the Pan American Union; Dr. Vera D. Rubin, director of the Research Institute for the Study of Man; and Dr. Richard P. Schaedel of the Institute of Latin American Studies at the University of Texas.
Access Restrictions
Some restricted materials pertaining mainly to internal finances, administration and private information remain at the Reed Foundation and are closed to researchers.
Additionally, please note that this collection is stored
offsite
, and you must contact the repository to schedule access.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Conference on Resources and Research in Haiti developed from a series of informal discussions between Dr. Richard P. Schaedel of the University of Texas and a small group of Haitian nationals working with international agencies in New York and Washington, D.C.. The Ford Foundation and the Joint Committee of the Social Science Research Council (SSRC) provided financial support for the conference. The Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM) and the City University of New York (CUNY) were responsible for organizing the event, which attracted participants from the Caribbean, Canada, Europe, Africa, South America, and the United States.
The primary goal of the conference was to lend support to Haiti by formulating short- and long-term solutions to the political and economic turmoil caused by the Duvalier government. However, participating scholars and professionals, representing the fields of economics, anthropology, psychology, political science, history, public health education, and library science, were also encouraged to develop common interests across their respective disciplines.
During the final plenary session of the conference, a provisional committee was organized to establish a permanent center for Haitian research. Founding members of the newly formed committee included Dr. Francois Latortue, who served as president, Dr. Emerson Douyon, vice president, and Mr. Max H. Dorsinville, executive secretary. Dr. Richard P. Schaedel and Dr. Vera Rubin held advisory roles. By March 1968 the provisional committee finalized its governing statutes for ratification, and the Center for Haitian Studies (CHS) was formally established as a permanent organization headed by an executive committee. All CHS operations were based at the headquarters of RISM.
In an attempt to keep the international community apprised of its activities, CHS published its first newsletter in October 1968, along with numerous research and training opportunities. With the financial assistance of RISM, committee members began organizing the November 1967 conference proceedings, which were eventually compiled and edited by Dr. Schaedel. Published as The Haitian Potential: Research and Resources of Haiti, high demand for the proceedings generated a second edition, published by Teachers College Press of Columbia University, in 1975.
Between 1969 and 1970, CHS sought ways to establish a permanent financial base and to actualize its goals through a yearly calendar of activities. The intent of these efforts was to gain greater access to research facilities and to provide funding for visiting scholars and postgraduate training endeavors. After conducting a search for affiliates and sponsors among American and Canadian Universities, CHS invited Dr. H. William Hutchinson of the University of Miami, Dr. Lambros Comitas of Teachers College, and Dr. Robert Rotberg of MIT to join its executive committee.
Dr. Rotberg organized a series of seminars on Haiti, co-sponsored by CHS and MIT. The seminars culminated in a second major conference, Culture and Development in Haiti, held at the University of Montreal in 1970. Following the conference, CHS executive committee members voted to transfer the Center's operations permanently to the University of Montreal.
Sources:
Final Report to the Ford Foundation, 1968 (Series II, folder 7)
"Center for Haitian Studies Established," press release, June 10, 1968 (Series III, folder 3)
"Haiti Research Group Planned," Miami Herald, November 11, 1967
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Center for Haitian Studies (CHS) span the years 1967-1975. The bulk of material was generated between 1967-1968. Materials in the bilingual collection include correspondence, financial records, reports, minutes, statutes, press releases, clippings, manuscripts, published conference proceedings, transcripts, articles, printed matter, audiotapes, notes, and ephemera. Specific details regarding chronological or alphabetical arrangement of the papers are included in the scope and content note for each series.
CHS was headquartered at RISM during a critical period in Haitian history. Their efforts to provide opportunities and a forum for Haitians living abroad or in exile are detailed in Series I. A contextual overview of Haiti, written as a rationale for the conference, can be found in several reports in Series II. Series III documents the specific goals, objectives, and accomplishments of CHS in correspondence, minutes, statutes, press releases and financial records. The formation of the CHS and its committee was also published in the Miami Herald in 1967 (see Series VII).
The largest series in the collection is Series IV. This series, which contains the files of conference participants, provides critical insight into all phases of the conference. Audio recordings of the conference are included. The collaborative efforts of CHS and MIT in sponsoring Haitian seminars are detailed in Series V.
Although there are fewer papers associated with the second Haitian Conference, the collaborative efforts of CHS and MIT are underscored in Series VI. Additional details concerning the conference can be found in the University of Montreal newspaper, Forum, Hebdo-Information De L'Universite De Montreal, published in May 1970. The newspaper can be found in Series X. A number of first-hand observations concerning the Haitian crisis are detailed in newspaper clippings in Series VII and X.
Series VIII includes correspondence and a wide range of publishing materials that highlight the committee's efforts to publish the conference proceedings. Series IX, the smallest series in the collection, contains brochures and print material representing the Center for Inter-American Relations. It remains unclear whether this organization formed a working relationship with CHS.
A copy of the published conference proceedings, Haitian Potential: Research and Resources of Haiti (Vera Rubin and Richard P. Schaedel, eds.) has been appended to the collection.
Arrangement
The Records of the Center for Haitian Studies (CHS) have been arranged in the following series:
I. Correspondence
II. Ford Foundation Grant Papers
III. Conference Papers: Research and Resources of Haiti
IV. CHS Committee Papers
V. Haiti Seminar Series
VI. Conference Papers: Culture and Development in Haiti
VII. Clippings
VIII. Publication Papers
IX. Miscellaneous Papers
X. Oversized Documents
Related Material
The Vera D. Rubin Papers, RISM RG 1, are located at the Reed Foundation.
Columbia University. Teachers College. Press.; Dorsinville, Max, 1943-; Douyon, Emerson; Duvalier, Francois, 1907-1971; Ford Foundation.; Latortue, François; Lomax, Alan, 1915-2002; Massachusetts Institute of Technology.; Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM).; Rubin, Vera D.; Schaedel, Richard P.; Université de Montréal.; Anthropology |z Haiti.; Audiotapes.; Clippings (information artifacts); Congresses and conventions |z Haiti.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents).; Financial records.; Haiti |x History.; Haiti.; Manuscripts (document genre).; Minutes.; New York (N.Y.); Reports.; transcripts.
- Series I. Correspondence, 1967-1972, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  .5 linear feet (1 box), arranged chronologically. This series consists of incoming and outgoing letters, budget material, book lists, greeting cards, notes and ephemera. The letters detail the formation, accomplishments and demise of the Center for Haitian Studies (CHS).
  - Correspondence, 1967 January-August (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1967 September-October (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1967 November-December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1968 January-March (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1968 April-June (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1968 July-October (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1968 November-December (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1969 January-March (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1969 April-June (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1969 July-August (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1969 September-December (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1970 January-February (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1970 March-September (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1971 February-May (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1971 June-November, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1972 January-December, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series II. Ford Foundation Grant Papers, 1967 - 1971, undated
  General note
  Materials in Series II are at the Reed Foundation.
  .5 linear feet (1 box), arranged chronologically. The papers in this series relate to conference funding and include expense sheets, correspondence, invoices, and reimbursement forms submitted by conference participants. Highlights include the Final report to the Ford Foundation, which provides a historical context and rationale for the conference. Box 2 containing Series II and part of Series III were returned to RISM March 2009.
- Series III. Conference Papers: Research and Resources of Haiti, 1967 - 1973, undated
  1.5 linear feet (3 boxes), arranged chronologically. The papers in this series document the activities and participants associated with the November 1967 conference and have been organized as three subseries. Subseries A includes pre-conference organizing, agendas and programs, administrative details, mailing lists, expense reports and summarized proceedings, which are also included in the CHS Committee Papers (Series IV). Subseries B consists of conference participant files, which have been retained in original alphabetical order by last name. These files include correspondence, curriculum vitae, articles, and manuscripts. Subseries C consists of reel-to-reel audiotapes. Box 4 containing part of Series III Subseries B. Conference Participants was returned to the Reed Foundation in March 2009.
  Some of the materials in Series III are at the Reed Foundation.
  - Subseries B. Conference Participants
    Some of the materials in Subseries B are the Reed Foundation.
    - Augier, Roy, 1967 October-December, 1968 July, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Bastien, Remy, 1967 July-December, 1968 July, 1968 August (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Bastien, Remy, 1970 January, 1971 February, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bazile, Robert, 1967 October, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Beaubrun, Michael H., 1967 September-December, 1968 January, 1968 July (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Benoist, Jean, 1967 September (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Bissainthe, Max, 1967 September-1968 May (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Berry, Paul G., 1968 July, 1968 November-1969 January, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Brea, Ernst T., 1967 October-November (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Brea, Ernst T., 1968 January-August, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Carroll, Eleanor E., 1967 October-November (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Dorsinville, Max H., 1967 August-November (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Dorsinville, Max H., 1967 November-December, 1968 January (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Lomax, Alan, 1967 November, 1968 January (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Lomax, Alan, 1968 January-December, 1969 January (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Pierre-Noel, Lucien, 1967 September-December, 1968 January (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Ravenscroft, Jr., Kent, 1967 November, 1968 January (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Roberts, G.W., 1967 September-November (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Stewart, William A., 1967 October (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Tinker, Edward Laroque, 1967 September (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Valdman, Albert, 1967 July-October, 1968 February-May (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Vielot, Kleber, 1967 July-October (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Vielot, Kleber, 1967 [November}-December (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Vieux, Serge A., 1967 August-December, 1968 January-December (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Vieux, Serge A., 1968 June (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Vieux, Serge A., 1973 February (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Subseries C. Reel-to-Reel Audiotapes
    - Tape 1, sides A & B, 1967 November (Box 6, Reel 1)
    - Tape 2 [no sides specified] Valdman, Berry & Elementary Education Tape 3, sides A & B, 1967 November (Box 6, Reel 2)
    - Tape 3, sides A & B, 1967 November (Box 6, Reel 3)
    - Tape 4, sides A & B Tape 5, sides A & B, 1967 November (Box 6, Reel 4)
    - Tape 5, sides A & B, 1967 November (Box 6, Reel 5)
    - Tape 6, side A only, 1967 November (Box 6, Reel 6)
    - 1st Part Tape 4, roll VIII, undated (Box 6, Reel 7)
- Series IV. CHS Committee Papers, 1967 - 1975, undated
  .75 linear feet (1 box, 4 folders), arranged chronologically. This bilingual series retraces the transition and development of CHS. The papers include correspondence, draft reports, draft and final versions of committee statutes, summarized proceedings of the November 1967 conference, meeting agendas, minutes, mailing lists, expense records, reimbursement forms, notes, and ephemera.
  - Correspondence, 1967 December (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Draft reports, amendments, 1968 January (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, manuscript, 1968 January (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1968 January-May (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, notes, 1968 February-December (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, resume of Haitian Conference [French, bound copy], list of participants, 1968 March (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Resume of Haitian Conference [French, bound copy], 1968 March (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Summary of conference proceedings [English, bound copy], [1968 March] (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, CHS statutes, 1968 March-April (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence [French], list of attendees, meeting agendas, detailed expenses, invoices, ephemera, 1968 May-June (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, mailing documents correspondence, news release, CHS statutes, amendement, Resume [French and English], notes, 1968 June-August (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Meeting agenda, list of expenses, correspondence, ephemera, 1968 November (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Notes, 1968 December (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, notes, 1969 January-November (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Notes, manuscript, 1969 March, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, meeting agendas, minutes, sample newsletters, expense forms, mailing list, notes, ephemera, 1969 May-June, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Mailing lists, correspondence, minutes, list of expenses, notes, ephemera, 1969 August-September, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, invitations, notes, list of expenses, ephemera, 1969 May-June (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, notes, list of expenses, ephemera, 1969 December (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, mailing lists, 1970 February-March (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - CHS Bulletin No. 1, notes, miscellaneous papers, 1970 April-May, 1971 February, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1970 July, 1972 November, 1975 February (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Series V. Haiti Seminar Series, 1969 - 1970, undated
  6 folders, arranged chronologically. This series documents the joint efforts of the Center for Haitian Studies and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology to produce seminars on Haitian issues. The papers include correspondence, mailing lists, invoices, minutes, notes, and ephemera.
  - Proposed schedule of seminars, mailing lists, correspondence, notes, 1969 January (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1969 February (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, notes, 1969 March (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, form letters, notes, mailing list, invoices, lists of expenses, notes, ephemera, 1969 April, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, participant list, invoices, list of expenses, invitation, notes, 1969 May-June (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1970 February-March (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Series VI. Conference Papers: Culture and Development in Haiti, 1969 - 1974, undated
  5 folders, arranged chronologically. This series consists of correspondence, brochures, invitations, flyers, programs, manuscripts, draft material and final reports. Highlights include an article concerning the CIA and Haiti, and flyers denouncing the Ford Foundation's funding of the conference.
  - Correspondence, 1969 August, 1970 January-March (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Article on the CIA and Haiti, flyers denouncing the 1970 conference, 1970 May, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Invitation, conference programs, final reports, 1970 May (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Conference programs, 1970 May (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Program information, draft material, manuscripts, correspondence, ephemera, 1970 May, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Publishing catalog, Sei, journal ayisyin aletrangje, ephemera, 1971, 1974 April, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Series VII. Clippings, 1967 - 1969, undated
  5 folders, arranged chronologically. The clippings in this series describe the formation, goals and accomplishments of CHS and the political climate in Haiti. Also included is an obituary of noted Haitian folklorist Dr. Jean Price-Mars.
  - Haiti Research Group Planned, Miami Herald, 1967 November (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Article outlining the goals of the center and its affiliates, note, Trans-cultural Psychiatric Research Vol. 5, 1968 October (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Center for Advanced International Studies, University of Miami, Journal of Inter-American Studies Vol. X, No. 4, 1968 October (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Haiti Conference Published, Newsletter of the American Anthropology Association, Vol. 10, No. 10, note, 1969 December, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Criado Centro de Estudos Haitianos, America Latina, ephemera, undated (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Obituary for Jean Price-Mars, published in Jeune Afrique and Le Nouvelliste, Mar 1969 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Editorial concerning the regime of Francois Duvalier, The Jamaican Daily Gleaner, 1969 July (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Report to O.A.S. Describes Charges of Terror in Haiti, N.Y. Times, 1969 August [?] (Box 8, Folder 24)
- Series VIII. Publication Papers, 1967 - 1976
  .5 linear feet (1 box), arranged chronologically. The papers in this series reflect the efforts of CHS members to publish Research and Resources of Haiti, the November 1967 conference proceedings. A limited run of the book was published by RISM in 1969. As a result of high demand, a second version was published by Teachers College in 1975. The papers include correspondence, price quotations, invoices, dedication page and table of contents, sample cover, application and certification of copyright, mailing lists, requests for publication copies, and book reviews.
  - Price quotations, invoices, correspondence, dedication page, table of contents, cover, note, Nov 1967, Dec 1968, May-Sept. 1969, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Copyright documents, invoices, book synopsis, correspondence, 1969 September-December (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Book reviews, correspondence, invoices, 1971 February-September, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Author questionnaire, Teachers College Press contract, correspondence, 1972 August-September (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Notes, 1972 October-November (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Teachers College Press Magazine Review List, CHS mailing lists, notes, 1973 January-July (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, mailing lists, notes, 1973 August-October (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, notes, ephemera, 1974 January-May (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, book reviews, 1975 May, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Book reviews, 1976 September-October (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, book advertisements from Teachers Press, 1976 October-November (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Research and Resources of Haiti, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Series X. Oversized Documents, 1969 - 1970
  2 folders, arranged chronologically. This series includes all oversized items in the collection.
  - The Times of the Americas, 1969 March (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Forum, Hebdo-Information De L'Universite De Montreal (3 copies), 1970 May (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Appendix